Guide to the Triangle Community Works Records, 1974-2008 RL.01309
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Triangle Community Works records
1974-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Triangle Community Works!
RL.01309
5.5 Linear Feet
Triangle Community Works! was formed in 1994 and consists of a coalition of groups, including ASPYN (A Safer Place Youth Network), The Gay and Lesbian Helpline, P-FLAG (Parents, Families, and Friends of Lesbians and Gays), and RRNGLE (Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality). Collection includes historical documents from several groups in Triangle Community Works!, including ASPYN, RRNGLE, and the Gay and Lesbian Helpline. Materials date from the 1970s to 2008.
4125 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection has restrictions. Helpline logs dated from 2004 onwards are closed. Please see the Detailed Description for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Triangle Community Works Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Historical Note
Triangle Community Works! is an organization that seeks to serve as a framework, a resource, and a partner to meet the emerging needs of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and other communities in the Greater Triangle area of North Carolina. It was formed in 1994 and consists of a coalition of groups, including ASPYN (A Safer Place Youth Network), The Gay and Lesbian Helpline, P-FLAG (Parents, Families, and Friends of Lesbians and Gays), and RRNGLE (Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality).
The Gay and Lesbian Helpline, which joined TCW! in 1996, began operating in 1991 as the first hotline for the gay and lesbian community in the Raleigh area. It offers peer counseling, education, information, and referrals for callers about anything from gay-friendly bars to AIDS education.
ASPYN, another component of TCW!, serves as a community safe haven for lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, questioning, and allied youth, ages 13-18.
More information about Triangle Community Works!, including their various programs and current activities, can be found on their website, http://www.tcworks.org/.
Collection Overview
This collection (Accession 2009-0276) includes historical documents from several groups in Triangle Community Works!, including ASPYN, RRNGLE, and the Gay and Lesbian Helpline. Materials date from the 1970s to 2008 and include news clippings, newsletters, publicity materials, meeting minutes, organizational records, and administrative files.
Collection Arrangement
Materials have only been refoldered when necessary for preservation. Please see below for a detailed folder list.
Gay youth; Helplines; Gays -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Same-sex marriage -- Laws and legislation -- United States; Religion and culture -- North Carolina -- Raleigh; Gays -- Religious life; Gay community -- North Carolina -- Raleigh; Gay teenagers -- Raleigh (N.C.); Triangle Community Works!; Triangle Community Works!; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- TCW! Series, 1994-2007, 1 box
  Scope and Contents
  The TCW! Series offers a helpful overview of the various programs within Triangle Community Works. Materials about the TCW! organization date from the 1990s through 2007. The TCW! materials include administrative files, such as meeting minutes, agendas, flyers, and publicity. Another notable part of the series is the TCW! financial files, which detail the organization's fiscal operations, including taxes, investments, and bank statements. The remainder of this series consists of press releases, newsletters, and ephemera from various events, such as pride marches. Also included is a binder of materials from Coalition 807, which predated Triangle Community Works! in the early 1990s, and newsletters from OutRight!, another organization within TCW!.
  - Flyers and posters from ASPYN and TCW! (Box 1)
  - TCW! administrative files and flyers, 1996 (Box 1)
  - TCW! finances (including bank statements, investments, reports, and taxes), 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - TCW! minutes and agendas, 1994-1996; 2000-2004; and 2006-2007 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Coalition 807 binder, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Advertisements, 1995 (Box 1)
  - News clippings (Box 1)
  - Press releases, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Pride March, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Pride March, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Organizational information (including tax forms, guidelines, by-laws), 1999 and no date (Box 1)
  - Fund for Southern Communities, 1994-2000s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous TCW! and Coalition 807 mail and correspondence, 1994-2004 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1994-1996 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - OutRight!, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - OutRight! articles, 1993 (Box 1)
  - OutRight! publicity and newsletters, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
- RRNGLE Resource Library Series, 1970s-1995, 3 boxes
  The RRNGLE Resource Library Series (Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality) makes up the majority of the Triangle Community Works Records. It consists of research and subject files collected and maintained by RRNGLE. Files are held within a variety of sub-series, including Religious Groups, Media coverage, Gay and Lesbian Organizations, and General subject files on topics from gay marriage to ordination of gay clergy. RRNGLE materials date largely from the late 1980s to the early 1990s, with some materials from the 1970s, but nothing post-1995.
  - Religious Groups (Box 1)
    - UCC: United Church Coalition for Gay and Lesbian Concerns, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - UCC open and affirming statements, 1988-1993 (Box 1)
    - National Gay and Pentecostal Alliance, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Jewish, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Metropolitan Community Church, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
    - Assembly of God, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Greek and Cyprist Orthadox, 1976-1991 (Box 1)
    - Southern Baptist, 1976-1994 (Box 1)
    - United Church of Canada, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Islam, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Society of Friends: Friends for Lesbian and Gay Concerns, 1989-1995
      - Friends for Lesbians and Gay Concerns newsletters, 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - Brethren/Mennonite Council for Lesbian and Gay Concerns, 1993-1994
      - Dialogue newsletters, 1978-1994 (Box 1)
    - Free Catholic Church/Ecumenical Catholic Church, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Unitarian Universalists
      - For Lesbian and Gay Concerns, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Welcoming Congregations, 1970-1992 (Box 1)
    - United Church Coalition WAVES newsletters, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Episcopal
      - Voice of Integrity newsletters, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Presbyrterian, 1989-1991
      - Presbyrterians for Lesbian and Gay Concern, 1992 (Box 1)
      - More Light Churches, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Seventh-Day Adventist, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Lutherans, 1970-1993
      - Lutherans Concerned, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
      - Reconciled in Christ, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Mormons, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - United Methodists, 1992-1994
      - Reconciling Congregations, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
      - Reconciling Pastors Action Network, 1993 (Box 2)
      - Affirmation (United Methodists for Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Concerns), 1991-1995 (Box 2)
      - Affirmation newsletters, 1990-1994 (Box 2)
    - Disciples of Christ/GLAD Alliance, 1991-1992
      - Crossbeams newsletters, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
    - Roman Catholics, 1984-1993
      - New Ways ministry, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
      - Conference of Catholic Lesbians, 1992 (Box 2)
      - Dignity, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
    - National Council of Churches, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - American Baptists Concerned, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Episcopal Church-Integrity, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - Women's Alliance for Theology, Ethics, and Ritual (WATER), 1994 (Box 2)
    - Evangelicals Concerned
      - Record newsletters, 1983-1993 (Box 2)
      - Reviews newsletters, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
  - Media Coverage
    - Second Stone newspapers, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
    - Stonewall News newspapers, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - 10 Percent magazines, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Our Own Community Press newspapers, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
    - POZ magazines, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - PFLAGpole newsletter, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous magazines and articles, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - Organizations
    - Human Rights Campaign Fund, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
    - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - ACLU, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - PFLAG, 1991-1992 and no date (Box 2)
    - NOW, 1991 (Box 2)
    - AIDS Service Agency for Wake County, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
    - Southern Poverty Law Center, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - North Carolinians Against Racist and Religious Violence, 1988-1993 (Box 2)
    - NC Coalition for Gay and Lesbian Equality, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
    - Lesbian and Gay Health Project, 1988-1994 (Box 3)
    - NC Pride PAC, 1991 and no date (Box 3)
    - Southeastern Conference for Lesbians and Gay Men, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Helpline, 1992 (Box 3)
    - NC Human Rights Fund, 1986 (Box 3)
    - National Lesbian and Gay Journalists Association, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Names Project, AIDS Quilt, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Gay Games, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Mary Renault Society of the Triangle, North Carolina, 1990 (Box 3)
    - AIDS Services Project, 1989 (Box 3)
    - AIDS National Interfaith Network, no date (Box 3)
    - Queen Nation, no date (Box 3)
    - Black and White Men Together, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Lesbian Herstory Archives, 1988 (Box 3)
    - College/university campus groups, 1984-1991 (Box 3)
    - Spectrum (Ministry of Light), 1992 (Box 3)
    - Campaign to End Homophobia, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
    - March on Washington, 1993 (Box 3)
    - St. John's Metropolitan Community Church, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - KKK and hate groups, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
    - Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, no date (Box 3)
    - National Gay Rights Advocates, 1990 (Box 3)
    - People for the American Way, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - Stonewall 25, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Subject files
    - General gay and lesbian coverage, 1988-1992 (Box 3)
    - Public opinion, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Religion and gays (general), 1979-1992 (Box 3)
    - Ordination of gay clergy, 1987-1991 (Box 3)
    - Pastor care, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Biblical passages, 1992-1993 and no date (Box 3)
    - Ethics, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
    - Holy unions, 1991-1992 and no date (Box 3)
    - Worship resources, no date (Box 3)
    - Legal issues, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
    - Domestic partner recognition, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
    - Sodomy laws, 1987-1992 (Box 3)
- ASPYN Series, 1990-2006, 1 box
  The ASPYN Series (A Safer Place Youth Network) includes materials dating from both before and after the group joined Triange Community Works!. Files predating TCW! include administrative and board materials, such as annual reports and meeting minutes. TCW! era materials include adult volunteer training manuals and policies, information for teenagers interested in joining ASPYN, evaluations by participants in ASPYN meetings and programs, and ASPYN call logs and group facilitator logs from the mid-1990s.
  - ASPYN prior to TCW! (Box 3)
    - Board meeting agendas (Box 3)
    - Board meeting minutes (Box 3)
    - Board member and volunteer lists (Box 3)
    - Policies and by-laws (Box 3)
    - Annual reports, resignations, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - ASPYN information, 2000s (Box 3)
  - Volunteer application package, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Advertising and brochures, no date (Box 3)
  - Training manual (Box 3)
  - Training (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, no date (Box 3)
  - Original documents, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Evaluations, 1996-1998 (Box 3)
  - Youth questionaires, 1995-1998 (Box 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Bank accounts and bills, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Call logs, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Youth group facilitator logs, 1994-1997 (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Helpline Series, 1990-2008, 4 boxes
  Access Restrictions
  Helpline logs dated 2004 and onward are closed. Please see Research Services or the Bingham Center staff with questions about this restriction.
  The Helpline Series includes materials ranging from the inception and formation of the Gay and Lesbian Helpline in 1991, through call logs from as recent as 2008. The series consists of administrative files, research articles on gay and lesbian hotlines, meeting minutes and agendas, newsletters and publications, and materials from the merging of the Helpline into the TCW! organization. The majority of the series, however, consists of the logbooks and call logs kept by volunteers tracking the calls received at the Helpline.
  - Formation, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 4)
  - Research articles (Box 4)
  - By-laws, finances, call summaries, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Meeting minutes, 1991-1996 (Box 4)
  - Agendas, 1994-1995 and no date (Box 4)
  - Newsletters and publicity, 1991-1995 (Box 4)
  - Merger with TCW!, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Logbooks of volunteer comments, 1991 October 7-1994 August 30 (3 books) (Box 4)
  - GLBT helpline logs, 1991 (Box 4)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 5), 1992 (Box 4)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 5), 1992 (Box 4)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 5), 1992 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (4 of 5), 1992 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (5 of 5), 1992 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 5), 1993 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 5), 1993 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 5), 1993 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (4 of 5), 1993 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (5 of 5), 1993 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 5), 1994 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 5), 1994 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 5), 1994 (Box 5)
  - GLBT helpline logs (4 of 5), 1994 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (5 of 5), 1994 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 3), 1995 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 3), 1995 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 3), 1995 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 5), 1996 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 5), 1996 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 5), 1996 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (4 of 5), 1996 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (5 of 5), 1996 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 3), 1997 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 3), 1997 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 3), 1997 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 3), 1998 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 3), 1998 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (3 of 3), 1998 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 2), 1999 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 2), 1999 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs, 2000-2001 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (1 of 2), 2001-2002 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (2 of 2), 2001-2002 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs, 2002 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs, 2003 (Box 6)
  - GLBT helpline logs (RESTRICTED), 2004 (Box 7)
  - GLBT helpline logs (RESTRICTED), 2005 (Box 7)
  - GLBT helpline logs (RESTRICTED), 2006 (Box 7)
  - GLBT helpline logs (RESTRICTED), 2007 (Box 7)
  - GLBT helpline logs (RESTRICTED), 2008 (Box 7)